Finding Aid for Michel Oksenberg papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Research and Other Projects
  - Chinese Energy Bureaucracy, with Kenneth Lieberthal
    - Readers' Comments, 1986-1987 (Box 33)
    - Recipients of Study, 1986-1987 (Box 33)
    - Report Drafts, 1985 (Box 33)
    - Research Proposals, 1983 (Box 33)
    - Three Gorges Dam, 1986 (Box 33)
  - Economic Decision-making, 1981 (Box 33)
  - Income Distribution Project, 1988-1989 (Box 33)
  - Posters and Charts from PRC, c. late, 1960s-1974 (Box 33)
  - Press clippings and Interviews, 1989 (Box 33)
  - Provincial Social Policy Project (James Tong)
    - Grant, 1983-1987 (Box 34)
    - Research Papers, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Research Paper Final Draft, 1989 (Box 34)
  - The Reform Conference: "To Reform the Chinese Political Order", June 1984
    - Correspondence and Conference Papers, 1982-1988; 9 folders (Box 34)
    - Session audiotapes, unprocessed, 1984; 19 audiocassettes (Box 34)
  - State Owned Enterprises Project, 1988; 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Tiananmen Project for M.E. Sharpe Publishers (with L. Sullivan), 1989-1990 (Box 35)
  - US-China Automotive Industry Cooperation Project, 1987-1989 (Box 35)
  - Interviews
    - Interviews with Oksenberg by M. Lampton about Carter Administration China Policy, transcripts and tapes, February, April 1983; 8 audiocassettes (Box 35)
    - Interview with Oksenberg about Carter Administration China Policy, interviewer unknown, May 1982; 5 audiocassettes (Box 35)
    - Interview with Oksenberg about Carter Administration China Policy, interviewer unknown (Richard Solomon?), October 1982; 2 audiocassettes (Box 35)
    - Oksenberg Seminar on summer research, October 1981; 1 audiocassettes (Box 35)
    - Woodcock, Leonard-Interview Transcripts, part of "Carter Administration China Policy Oral History Project", 1981-1982; 7 folders 38 tape transcripts; transcript missing for tape #39; also two cassettes of LW press conference (Box 35)
  - Trip and Interview Journals
    - China Trips
      - NCUSCR, 1972-1982; 3 folders (Box 36)
      - Atlantic Council, 1983 (Box 36)
      - Trip with Kenneth Lieberthal, includes interviews for the Chinese Energy Bureaucracy Project, May 1985 (Box 36)
    - University of Michigan: Interviews with Zhu Jiaming, November 1985 (Box 36)
    - China Trips
      - Trip with Zbigniew Brzezinski: includes interviews with Li Peng and Hu Yaobang, summer 1986 (Box 36)
      - Trip with Harold Jacobson: interviews for the World Bank Study-China's Entry in the World Bank, IMF, and GATT, summer 1986 (Box 36)
    - Taiwan Notes, February 1987 (Box 36)
    - United Nations Association, May 1987 (Box 36)
    - Moscow, USSR/UNISYS, October 1988 (Box 36)
  - Notes of interviews with Chinese refugees
    - 1960s, 1970s conducted by Oksenberg and others in Hong Kong, 1960-1979 (Box 16)
  - Research Trips (Box 65)
  - Research Trips (Box 66)
    (continued)
  - Research Trips (Box 67)
- Consulting
  The Consulting series consists of correspondence, memoranda, and reports which document Oksenberg's role as a consultant to businesses and law firms after the opening of relations with the PRC. Most of the series is the result of his work as "Advisor on China Matters" to a Washington, DC law firm.
  - Business
    - Boeing Commercial Airlines, 1980-1988 (Box 37)
    - Chemical Bank, 1985 (Box 37)
    - Chrysler Motors Corp., 1988 (Box 37)
    - Motorola Inc., 1984-1985 (Box 37)
    - UNISYS (Burroughs), 1985-1989 (Box 37)
  - Legal
    - Akin, Gump, Strauss, Hauer, & Feld, Washington D.C. Law firm
      - "Advisor on China Matters" Correspondence, 1986-1991; 3 folders (Box 37)
      - ACB International, Ltd., 1988-1989 (Box 37)
      - AT&T, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 37)
      - China Onshore Oil Project Briefing Book, 1988; 2 folders (Box 37)
      - Chinese Beer, 1989 (Box 37)
      - CITIC (China International Trust and Investment Corp.), 1989 (Box 37)
      - Civil Aviation Administration of China, 1987 (Box 37)
      - Cogentrix, Inc., 1988 (Box 37)
      - GCA Corp, 1988-1989 (Box 37)
      - Guardian Industries Corp., 1988-1989 (Box 37)
      - Morgan Stanley, 1987-1988 (Box 37)
      - Triton Energy Corp., 1987-1989; 5 folders (Box 37)
    - Baker and McKenzie Law Firm, 1986; 2 folders (Box 38)
- Topical files, 1970s-1980s
  The Topical Files series consists of correspondence, reports, trip itineraries and memoranda. The contents of the series are diverse; they include information about Jimmy Carter's presidential campaigns, and an unpublished campaign briefing on China by Oksenberg.
  - Association for Asian Studies, 1974-1975 (Box 45)
  - Bibliography of Secondary English Language Literature on Contemporary Chinese Politics, circa 1970 (Box 45)
  - Brzezinski China Trip, 1981 (Box 45)
  - Carter Campaign Briefing, unpublished manuscript, 1980 (Box 45)
  - Carter China Trip, 1981 (Box 45)
  - Carter for President, 1976-1980; 2 folders (Box 45)
  - Central Intelligence Agency Briefing, 1974 (Box 45)
  - China Quarterly (journal), 1980-1985 (Box 45)
  - Article Reviews, 1985-1989 (Box 45)
  - China Task Force (UM), 1980 (Box 45)
  - Chinese Studies Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 45)
  - Correspondence
    - A-Z, 1977-1982 (Box 45)
    - Personal, 1977-1981 (Box 45)
  - Department of State Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation, 1986-1990 (Box 45)
  - Dissertation Comments, 1968-1969 (Box 45)
  - Eckstein, Alexander, Obituary, 1977 (Box 46)
  - Evaluation for Promotion, 1975-1976 (Box 46)
  - Fundraising
    - Center for Chinese Studies, 1973-1974 (Box 46)
    - Contacts, 1975 (Box 46)
    - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 46)
    - Interviews, 1975 (Box 46)
    - Kissinger Meetings, 1976 (Box 46)
    - Memoranda and Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 46)
  - Greenhills School Correspondence, 1987 (Box 46)
  - Jackson, Senator Henry M. (Scoop), 1980-1982 (Box 46)
  - Lee Hong Yung, manuscript review, undated (Box 46)
  - Luce Foundation Fund for Chinese Scholars, 1981-1988 (Box 46)
  - National Defense University, 1980-1989 (Box 46)
  - National Science Foundation Research Proposals and Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 46)
  - National Security Council Security Clearance, 1977-1981 (Box 46)
  - Normalization, 1979-1980 (Box 46)
  - O'Reilly for Congress-Congressional Briefing Paper, 1980 (Box 46)
  - Red Guard, 1967 (Box 46)
  - Reprint Request Letter, 1980 (Box 46)
  - Scholarly Exchange Paper, 1975 (Box 46)
  - Shapiro, Harold-Trip to China, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 46)
  - US Department of State, 1979-1985 (Box 46)
  - University of California-San Diego, 1986-1987 (Box 46)
  - University of Chicago-Luce Seminar in American-Asian Cultural Relations, 1980 (Box 46)
  - University of Michigan Business School Seminar, 1975 (Box 46)
  - University of Pittsburgh Evaluation, 1987-1988 (Box 46)
  - Visit of Ambassador Chai, 1980 (Box 46)
  - Visit of Vice Premier Deng Xiaoping, 1979 (Box 46)
  - Visit to Sao Paulo, 1976 (Box 46)
  - Workshop and Conference on the "Pursuit of Political Interest in the People's Republic", 1977 (Box 46)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes pictures of Oksenberg which date mainly from his tenure at the NSC, as well as pictures taken at official functions and on trips to China.
  - China, 1976-1978 (Box 46)
  - Conferences, circa 1970s (Box 46)
  - Defense Strategy Seminar, 1977 (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous, including portraits, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 46)
- China-Special Files
  The China - Special Files are materials kept separate by Michel Oksenberg for their significance. Much of the material concerns trips (and preparations for trips) to China made by Oksenberg and other dignitaries mainly in the 1980s although some of documents date back to the Carter Administration. There are also several volumes and notepads of notes made by Oksenberg following conversations with individuals on subjects relating to U.S.-China relations.
  - Notes-Interviews, China Trip, Summer 1986
    - Zbigniew Brzezinski-Oksenberg (Box 68)
    - Harold Jacobson-Oksenberg (Box 68)
  - Memoranda of conversation (Carter administration), 1977-1981 (Box 68)
  - Notes and memoranda regarding preparation for, and visit of, President Nixon to China, 1989 (Box 68)